A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, Public Relations, Series 27 FA369
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, Public Relations, Series 27
1958-1972
Rockefeller Archive Center
New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Cannon, James M.
Ronan, William J. (William John)
Whitman, Ann
New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights
Morrow, Hugh
Boyd, Joseph H.
FA369
4 record cartons
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 15 27
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
This series is divided into three subseries:
Subseries 1 - Books and Articles, 1960-1971 Subseries 2 - Speeches, 1960-1964 Subseries 3 - Campaign Material, 1958-1972
Scope and Contents note
NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
This series contains a small portion of the office fils of Hugh Morrow. They document his official activities in the execution of his duties as a member of Nelson A. Rockefeller's gubernatorial staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration and political campaigns. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed that he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller which were never shown to him.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This series contains a small portion of the files of Hugh Morrow, who served as a speech writer and special assistant to Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller from November 1959 and was appointed Director of Communications on February 4, 1969.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, James Cannon (FA356)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Counsel's Office (FA358)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Jerry A. Danzig (FA360)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Issue Books (FA363)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Office (FA365)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, William J. Ronan (FA371)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial (FA374)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Gene Wyckoff (FA375)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Public policy; Economics; Federal government -- United States; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Public relations; State governments -- United States; United States; Vice-Presidents -- United States; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Latin America; Legislation -- New York (State); New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Human rights; International economic relations; International relations; International relations -- United States; Arms control -- United States; Arms control; Affirmative action programs -- New York (State); Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Civil service -- New York (State); Civil service; Civil defense -- United States; Civil defense; New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Cannon, James M.; Ronan, William J. (William John); Whitman, Ann; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights; Morrow, Hugh; Boyd, Joseph H.
- Books and Articles, 1960-1971; 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries consists of drafts and correspondence regarding articles either prepared by Rockefeller or written for him by Morrow and others. Published copies are included for most of the articles. However, some files do not indicate whether publication actually occurred. This section includes correspondence on the production of three books by Rockefeller. They include "Unity, Freedom and Peace," Rockefeller's stand on various issues written for the 1968 presidential race; "Dear Mr. President," an unpublished book on foreign policy drafted by Rodney Campbell; and "Our Environment Can Be Saved," Rockefeller's 1970 strategy for saving the environment and supporting the arts. There are slim files on two other books: "The Future of Federalism," the book version of Rockefeller's 1962 talks at Harvard University's Godkin Lecture Series; and "The Real Rockefeller," Frank Gervasi's 1964 biography. There are no drafts for any of the books, including "Dear Mr. President." Copies of the published books are found in the Archive Center library.
  - Articles Requested for Publication - Miscellaneous, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Drafts and correspondence re articles requested of NAR. Subjects include "Words to Live By"; how to keep peace in the Latin American family; fundamental American values; government service; favorite stories; Republican issues - Richard Peet and James Wills; 1964 strategy; today's issues (1964); Republican policy re Negroes; attack Goldwater; scientific research in New York.
  - "County Government", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Article by NAR; "The Importance of Local Government."
  - North American Newspapers Alliance Series, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Drafts of 6 articles: 1) Economic Growth; 2) Public Finance; 3) Education; 4) Housing; 5) Health; and 6) Civil Defense (fall-out shelters).
  - "Foreign Affairs", April 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Article by NAR: "Purpose and Policy," (five areas of foreign policy: 1) negotiations with Soviet Union; 2) military security; 3) arms control; 4) economic goals; and 5) values.)
  - "Newsweek", July 25, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Article by NAR: "A Way to Bind Africa to the Free World." Folder includes one draft entirely in NAR's handwriting.
  - "This Week", June 11, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sunday supplement magazine article by NAR: "Some Advice for the Class of 61." (Discusses conflict betwen those who believe in the supreme worth of the individual and those who believe the individual to be but a cog in the machinery of a tyrannical state.)
  - "Marina International", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Article by NAR: "New York's Boating Partnership Program." (To meet the needs of the "trailer-sailor.")
  - Local Government, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Statement by NAR to Westchester Community Growth Conference on role of local government, "State can be of real assistance."
  - Victor Riesel guest column, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Economic Growth (1960) and Automation (1961).
  - "American Banker", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Article by NAR on economic growth.
  - "County Government", July 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Article by NAR: "Governor's Regional Government Plan." Correspondence, memos and drafts.
  - "The Future of Federalism", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    NAR's Godkin Lectures at Harvard University in book format. (These annual lectures on "The Essentials of Free Government and the Duties of the Citizen" were established in 1902 in memory of newpaper editor Edwin Lawrence Godkin.)
  - "U.S. News & World Report", September 17, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Article by NAR: "A Plan for Growth and Jobs." (p.108) Correspondence, drafts, background material.
  - Time Magazine article, June 15, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    NAR portrait by Henry Koerner on cover; article, "The Republicans" (7 copies). Correspondence with Reader's Digest on reprinting Time article; NAR handwritten note on Hugh Morrow's memo: "Hugh, Congratulations. It's Terrific."
  - Victor Riesel guest column, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Article by NAR: "Political Labels."
  - "Saturday Evening Post", March 1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Article by NAR: "Political Labels are Nonsense."
  - Victor Riesel guest column, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Article by NAR theorizing that the most important civil rights legislation could be tax cut legislation which would create more job opportunities. Final has NAR handwritten edits.
  - "The Real Rockefeller", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Biography by Frank Gervasi. Correspondence re purchase of 10,000 copies for use in California; bill from publisher.
  - "Rebirth at the Grass Roots", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Sanford Lecture at Delhi University, September 28, 1966. Drafts of lecture, gift of manuscript to Delhi University. Final draft memo to NAR from Hugh Morrow has NAR handwritten note: "Hugh, Wonderful. Many Thanks! Nelson." Correspondence with Delhi Univ. professor on manuscript being readied for publication.
  - "Parent's Magazine", May 1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Article by NAR: "We Honor Our Teachers." (2 copies of magazine.) Background material re"Teacher Recognition Day" in New York 1960-1966.
  - Federalism, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    NAR review for Sunday "New York Times" of book by Terry Sanford, North Carolina Governor 1961-1965, "Storm Over the States."
  - Culture, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    NAR tribute to Mrs. August Belmont for "Opera News." NAR handwritten edits of draft by Hugh Morrow.
  - Politics, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Pamphlet, with statement by NAR, to create a State University of New York Scholarship; "The Jane H. Todd Memorial Scholarship." Todd elected to New York State Assembly in 1934; became first woman Deputy Commissioner of Commerce.
  - Office of Governor, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Proposed article for "Newsday" requested by Bill Moyers, publisher. Drafts of ararticle on the role of governor today and need for block grants to states from Federal Government.
  - Government and Society, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    NAR article for January, 1968 issue of Foreign Affairs: "Policy and the People." Memos by Henry A. Kissinger; drafts; correspondence; NAR handwritten notes to Ann (Whitman) and edits; Hugh Morrow 12/27/67 memo to NAR (with article reprints) on which NAR writes "Hugh, Many thanks for all you did on this! I think it came out very well."
  - "Good Housekeeping", February 1968 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    "Exclusive: The Rockefellers ar Home." Cover story.
  - New York State Urban Development Corporation, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    2/27/68 press release of Special Message to Legislature on creation of Urban Development Corporation; transcript of NAR press conference re Special Message; background notes; drafts of Program Bills; Hugh Morrow memo 4/2/68 to NAR for clearance of Urban Development Corporation pamphlet with handwritten "OK NAR."
  - Everson Museum of Art, Syracuse, New York, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    NAR statement on opening of new building; correpondence re statement; Hugh Morrow transmitting statement to NAR with NAR handwritten "Hugh Wonderful Thanks Nelson."
  - "Unity, Freedom & Peace", 1968 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Correspondence with Random House re book to be produced by Rodney Campbell; comments by staff to NAR; drafts of dust cover promotional copy; memos re costs and distribution of book; 1 copy of book.
  - "Year 1969, The Encyclopedia News Annual", 1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    NAR preface to year book.
  - Hospital Financial Management Newsletter, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    NAR article on Universal Health Insurance; correspondence; draft; Hugh Morrow clearance memo to NAR with NAR handwritten "Hugh Excellent Check Al on opening paragraph Thanks Nelson."
  - "New York", March 1969 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    NAR article on what the state has done for the arts; correspondence; drafts, March 5 draft with NAR handwritten edits; final version dated March 11.
  - "Modulus", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Annual Journal of School of Architecture, University of Virginia; Article: "A Modern Federalism for an Urban America"; correspondence; memos; draft; 2 copies of Journal.
  - "Dear Mr. President", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Book on foreign policy to be produced by Rodney Campbell; undated (late 1968?) from Rodney Campbell to Hugh Morrow; correspondence Hugh Morrow with Random House.
  - "Oceans", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Draft of article: "New York Looks at Its Future on the Great Lakes."
  - "American Banker", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Article: Pure Waters Program, Urban Job Incentive Board, Interracial Council for Business Opportunity and Urban Development Corporation.
  - "Eye", 1968 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Article: "The Current Generation." (May not have gone to press.)
  - Victor Riesel guest column, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Column on the fiscal crisis in the federal government and need to make federal block grants to states and local governments.
  - "Sources", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Blue Cross magazine. Request for article; draft article on Universal Health Insurance; memos; memo Hugh Morrow to NAR 7/24/69 attaching article for clearance; NAR handwritten note "Hugh Thanks OK Have Al's people checked out? Nelson One minor suggestion." Transmittal by Hugh Morrow to Blue Cross 7/29/69.
  - "Newsday", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    "The Rockefeller Years"; 5 part series 4/14-18/69.
  - "American Banker", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Article by NAR: "Long Island - Growth is the Name of the Game."
  - "Salesman", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Article by NAR: "Growth in the Seventies - A Forecast."
  - "Trial", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Article by NAR: "Equity and Order in Public Employment." Basis for and enactment of the "Taylor Law" (prohibits strikes by public employees).
  - "Water and Wastes Engineering", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Article by NAR: "A Livable Environment - Mission for the Seventies."
  - "Archives of Internal Medicine", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Article by NAR: "Universal Health Care Insurance is the Wave of the Future."
  - "The Forensic Quarterly", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Article by NAR: "A Livable Environment - It Can Be Done."
  - "The Designer", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Article by NAR: "Building a Second America."
  - "Lodging and Food Service News", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Article by NAR: "Tourism in the 70s - Count on New York State."
  - "The Evening News" (Newburgh, New York), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Article by NAR for special edition: 22nd Anniversary of Israel.
  - "Brandon's Shipper and Forwarder", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Article by NAR: "New York State and Export Expansion."
  - "New York State Town and County Government", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Article by NAR: "When Peace Breaks Out" urging local legislators to organize post-Vietnam planning committees.
  - "Nation's Business", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Article by NAR: "New York State's Business Talent Reservoir."
  - "American Banker", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Article by NAR: "Working Together To Save the Environment."
  - Albany Times Union, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    Supplement, Fifth Anniversary of Saratoga Performing Arts Center. NAR handwritten note on Hugh Morrow memo to NAR: "OK, Excellent. Might it not be appropriate for me to mention that I was proud of the fact that my wife was Ch. of the Board?"
  - Victor Reisel guest column, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    NAR article on organized crime and the new Statewide Prosecutor.
  - "Personal Finance Law Quarterly Report", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    Article by NAR: "The Consumer and the 1970 Legislative Session in New York."
  - "Our Environment Can Be Saved", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    Proposal (1/22/70) from Rodney Campbell; memos and correspondence re book project, negotiations with publishers; forward by John W. Gardner (former Secretary of (United States Department of) Health, Education and Welfare); drafts of dust cover, political memos.
  - "Our Environment Can Be Saved", 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Book Reviews; clippings; requests for book.
- Speeches, 1960-1964; 2
  This subseries consists of files on 49 speeches made by Governor Rockefeller from 1960 to 1964, which is only a small portion of the many speeches he made during this period. Folders 59 through 69 contain speeches made prior to the Republican National Convention of 1960. Speeches in folders 81 through 102 provide an indication of Rockefeller's ambition to seek the Republican Presidential nomination in 1964. The contents of each file vary and may include handwritten drafts by Rockefeller, typed drafts with Rockefeller's handwritten edits, printed transcripts for press releases, and correspondence.
  - "The Third Century", April 22, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Speech subtitled: "A Concept of American Foreign Policy."
  - "Man and Law", May 1, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    Speech subtitled: "An Appraisal of the Moral Foundations of Law in a Free Society"; given at Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, University of Chicago.
  - "A Civil Rights Program for the United States", June 17, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Speech; given at Buffalo, New York to National Sunday School and Baptist Training Union Congress.
  - "Great Design for Freedom", June 21, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    Speech subtitled: "A Program to Strengthen the Structure of Our Own Government and the Bonds of the Free World"; Binghamton, New York, Rotary Club.
  - "The 1960s: Decade of Danger", June 28, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Speech subtitled: "And a Program to Meet It"; National Governors' Conference.
  - "Health Care for the Aged", June 29, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    Statement subtitled: "A Program and a Workable Approach"; National Governors' Conference.
  - "The Problem of Arms and Arms Control", July 8, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    Statement subtitled: "An Analysis and Program Oriented to Our National Goals."
  - "Better Education for Americans", July 9, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    Statement subtitled: "A Financial Program to Meet this Mounting Challenge."
  - "A Republican Approach to the Great Issues", July 11, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    Submission to the Platform Committee of the Republican National Committee.
  - "Western Hemisphere Unity", July 12, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    Speech subtitled" "An Action Program to Counter the Communist Threat by Strengthening Democracy and Freedom"; New York Young Republican Club.
  - "Let Freedom Ring", July 19, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    A Centennial Memorandum for the 1960 Republican Party Platform submitted to the Republican Platform Committee in Chicago, Illinois.
  - "Higher Education", January 31, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    Legislative Document No. 9, Special Message to the Legislature.
  - "Power to Save Freedom", October 27, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    Speech (press release) to National Convention of Sigma Delta Chi, Miami, Florida, making the case for nuclear testing.
  - "No Test Ban Now", November 14, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    Statement subtitled: "Further Nuclear Testing is Vital in Face of Soviet Duplicity and Threat to World Freedom."
  - "Basic Republican Precepts", January 24, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    Speech (handwritten) to Minnesota Republican Fund Raiser, St. Paul, Minnesota.
  - "Mental Disability", January 30, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    Legislative Document No. 9, Message to the Legislature.
  - "Medical Assistance for the Aged", March, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    A report based upon experience under 1961 State legislation.
  - "Medical Care for the Aged", May 1, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    Speech subtitled: "Social Security and Freedom of Choice"; Statewide Conference on the Aging, New York City.
  - "New York: A State Can Meet Its Responsibilities", August, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    Republican State Committee pamphlet.
  - "Jobs and Prosperity", December 5, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    Speech to Congress of American Industry, National Association of Manufacturers, Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, New York City.
  - Second Inaugural Address, January 1, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Annual Message to the Legislature, January 9, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - "Nuclear Testing and Free World Security", January 28, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    Press Release.
  - "National Security", January 29, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    Speech subtitled: "The People's Right and Need to Know the Facts"; Albany; New York State Publishers Association.
  - "Our Troubled Alliance and the Future of Freedom", February 9, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    Press Release, Chicago, Illinois.
  - "Civil Rights", February 12, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    Lincoln Birthday Address, New York City.
  - "Promise and Performance on Civil Rights", March 5, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    Speech, Albany, to New York State Conference of National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Branches.
  - "Tax Incentives for Growth and More Jobs Now", March 9, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    Press Release, Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
  - "20 Million New Jobs", April 6, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    Press Release, Omaha, Nebraska, subtitled: "A Program for Growth."
  - "A Matter of Principle", July 14, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    Press Release, Albany. (File folder: "radical right statement.")
  - "Freedom and the American Way of Life", July 27, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    Speech at Bohemian Grove, San Francisco, California; speech outline with NAR handwritten notes.
  - "The Nuclear Test Ban Treaty", August 12, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    Press release with background memorandum; Albany.
  - "Principle vs. Opportunism - the Responsibility of Power", September 4, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    Speech, New York City, to Annual Meeting of American Political Science Association.
  - "The Kennedy Administration - a Record of Failure", September 7, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    Speech, Oregon, Illinois, Republican rally and picnic; draft of speech.
  - "The Republican Party in New York State", September 16, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    NAR handwritten notes for speech, Ulster County, New York, Republican Committee.
  - "Broken Promises on the New Frontier", September 21, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    Speech, Huntington, West Virginia, Republican Finance Committee of West Virginia.
  - Local Government, September 22, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 95)